<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ansvver of the Parliament of the Commonwealth of England, to three papers delivered in to the Councel of State by the lords ambassadors extraordinary of the States General of the United Provinces. As also a narrative of the late engagement between the English fleet under the command of General Blake; and the Holland fleet under the command of Lieutenant Admiral Trump. And likewise severall letters, examinations and testimonies touching the same. Together with the three papers, aforesiad of the said lords ambassadors extraordinary; and the letter of Lieutenant Admiral Trump therein mentioned, translated into English.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82541</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1228</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E668_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206950</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866034</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866034</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166192</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82541)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166192)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 102:E668[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ansvver of the Parliament of the Commonwealth of England, to three papers delivered in to the Councel of State by the lords ambassadors extraordinary of the States General of the United Provinces. As also a narrative of the late engagement between the English fleet under the command of General Blake; and the Holland fleet under the command of Lieutenant Admiral Trump. And likewise severall letters, examinations and testimonies touching the same. Together with the three papers, aforesiad of the said lords ambassadors extraordinary; and the letter of Lieutenant Admiral Trump therein mentioned, translated into English.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Field, printed to the Parliament of England,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes letters signed by M. Harperts Trump, Robert Blake, William Brandley and others.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 17.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anglo-Dutch War, 1652-1654 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History, Naval --  Stuarts, 1603-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166192:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANSWER OF THE PARLIAMENT of the Commonwealth of ENGLAND, TO THREE PAPERS Delivered in to the COUNCEL of STATE By the Lords Ambaſſadors Extraordinary of the States General of the UNITED PROVINCES.</p>
            <p>As alſo a NARRATIVE Of the late Engagement between the ENGLISH Fleet under the Command of General <hi>Blake;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the <hi>Holland</hi> Fleet under the Command of Lieutenant Admiral <hi>Trump.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And likewiſe ſeveral LETTERS, EXAMINATIONS and TESTIMONIES touching the ſame.</p>
            <p>Together with the Three PAPERS aforeſaid of the ſaid Lords Ambaſſadors Extraordinary; And the LETTER of Lieutenant Admiral <hi>Trump</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in mentioned, Tranſlated into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Field,</hi> Printer to the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="response">
            <pb facs="tcp:166192:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:166192:2"/>
            <head>The <hi>ANSWER</hi> of the Parliament of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>England,</hi> to Three Papers preſented to them by the Councel of State, from the Ambaſſadors Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary of the Lords the States General of the United Provinces; The Firſt whereof is dated the Third of <hi>June,</hi> the Second the Sixth of <hi>June,</hi> and the Third the Thirteenth of <hi>June, 1652. new Stile,</hi> upon occaſion of the late Fight between the Fleets.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> calling to minde with what continued Demonſtrations of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſincere Affections, from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beginning of their inteſtine Troubles they have proceeded towards their Neighbors of the United Provinces, omitting nothing on their part that might conduce to a good correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with them, and to a growing up into a more near and ſtrict Union then formerly, Do finde themſelves much ſurprized with the unſutable Returns that have been made thereunto, and eſpecially at the Acts of Hoſtility lately committed in the very Roads of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> upon the Fleet of this Commonwealth, the matter of Fact whereof ſtated in clear Proofs, is hereunto annexed; Upon ſerious and deliberate conſideration of all, and of the ſeveral Papers delivered in by Your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies to the Councel of State, the Parliament thinks fit to give this Anſwer to thoſe Papers:</p>
            <p>The Parliament, as they would be willing to make a charitable conſtruction of the Expreſſions uſed in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166192:3"/>ſaid Papers, endeavoring to repreſent the late Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Fleets to have hapned without the knowledge, and againſt the minde of Your Superiors; So when they conſider how diſagreeable to that profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion the Reſolutions and Actions of Your State and their miniſters at Sea have been, even in the midſt of a Treaty offered by themſelves, and managed here by Your Excellencies, the extraordinary Preparations of One hundred and Fifty ſail of Men of War, without any viſible occaſion but what doth now appear (a juſt ground of Jealouſie in Your own judgments, when Your Lordſhips pretended to excuſe it) and the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions themſelves given by Your ſaid Superiors to their Commanders at Sea, Do finde too much cauſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, That the Lords the States General of the United Provinces have an Intention, by Force to uſurp the known Rights of <hi>England</hi> in the Seas, to deſtroy the Fleets that are, under God, their Walls and Bulwarks, and thereby expoſe this Commonwealth to Invaſion at their pleaſure, as by this late Action they have attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted to do: Whereupon the Parliament conceive they are obliged to Endeavor, with Gods aſſiſtance, as they ſhall have opportunity, To ſeek Repairation of the Wrongs already ſuffered, and Security that the like be not attempted for the future.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, with this minde and deſire, That all Differences betwixt the Nations may (if poſſibly) be peaceably and friendly compoſed, as God by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence ſhall open a way thereunto, and Circumſtances ſhall be conducing to render ſuch Endeavors leſs dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and more effectual then thoſe of this kinde here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore uſed have been.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen: Scobell, Cleric. Parliamenti.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:166192:3"/>
            <head>A Narrative of the late Engagement betwen the Engliſh Fleet under the Command of General <hi>Blake,</hi> and the Holland Fleet under the Command of Lieutenant Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral <hi>Trump</hi> near <hi>Dover.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>UPon Tueſday the Eighteenth of <hi>May</hi> 1652. in the morning, General <hi>Blake</hi> being gone to the Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward as far as <hi>Rye</hi> Bay eight days before with twelve or thirteen Ships, leaving Major <hi>Bourn</hi> in the <hi>Downs</hi> with eight Ships onely, there appeared upon the backſide of the <hi>Goodwin</hi> a <hi>Holland</hi> Fleet of Men of War conſiſting of two and forty Ships, one whereof had a Flag on the main-top-Maſt head, the reſt Jacks and Ancients; and being come unto the South-ſands head, two of them bore up towards the Engliſh Ships in the <hi>Downs,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Major <hi>Bourn</hi> ſent out the <hi>Greyhound</hi> to examine them, and to know the reaſon of their ſo near approach; who anſwering, That they had a Meſſage to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chief in the <hi>Downs,</hi> were permitted to come in, and having ſaluted the Flag, the two Captains na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Tyſon</hi> and <hi>Aldred</hi> came Aboard the ſaid Major <hi>Bourn,</hi> and acquainted him that they were ſent by <hi>Van Trump</hi> to let him know that he had been Riding about <hi>Dunkirk</hi> with his Fleet, where by reaſon of foul Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they had loſt many of their Cables and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chors, and the wind being Northerly, were driven fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Southward then they intended, which <hi>Van Trump</hi> thought fit to ſignifie to prevent any miſappre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions or Jealouſies. And having ſaid this, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived for anſwer, That the Reality of what they ſaid would beſt appear by their ſpeedy drawing off from this Coaſt, they departed to their Fleet; and immediately upon their arrival with them, the whole Fleet ſtood up
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:166192:4"/>to <hi>Dover,</hi> and came to an Anchor within little more then ſhot of the Caſtle the ſame day in the afternoon. Upon their coming before <hi>Dover</hi> Caſtle, and Riding there with Flag in the Main-top, without ſaluting the Caſtle, the Caſtle made three ſhot at them; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding which, the Dutch Admiral kept up his Flag, and rode there at Anchor until the next day noon, and exerciſed his Muſquetiers, by diſcharging Volleys of ſmall ſhot many hours together. Upon Wedneſday about twelve a clock the Dutch Fleet weighed Anchor and ſtood off towards <hi>Calice</hi> ſome four Leagues into the South-eaſt; about the ſame time the Engliſh Fleet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der General <hi>Blake</hi> coming from the Weſt towards the <hi>Downs</hi> diſcovered them, and ſuppoſed by their courſe they had been going back; Major <hi>Bourn</hi> likewiſe was in ſight, coming from the <hi>Downs</hi> to joyn with General <hi>Blake.</hi> About an hour or two after, the Holland Fleet altered their courſe, came back again, made all the Sail they could, and bore directly with General <hi>Blake, Van Trump</hi> the headmoſt with his Flag in the Main-top; and being come within ſhot, the General ſhot a Gun at his Main-top, and then two ſingle ſhot more: whereupon <hi>Trump</hi> ſhot a ſingle ſhot through the Generals Flag, and then immediately gave the firſt Broad-ſide and took in his Pendants, and hung out his Red Flag under the Holland Colours, which was the Signal on their part for their whole Fleet to ingage, and ſo the Fight began, which happened between four and five a clock in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon, and continued until nine of the clock. In the Fight the Engliſh took two of the Holland Fleet, one whereof having ſix foot water in the Hold they left, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Captain and Officers aboard, the other being a Ship of thirty Guns. General <hi>Blake</hi> lay all night
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:166192:4"/>where the Fight began, or near thereabouts, and the Holland Fleet was eſpyed about four Leagues diſtant towards the Coaſt of <hi>France</hi> next morning.</p>
            <p>The truth of this Relation appears in the Letters of General <hi>Blake,</hi> Major <hi>Bourn,</hi> and others in the Action, by the Examinations of the Dutch Captains, and other Officers taken in the Fight; the Inſtructions given to the Dutch Captains and Commanders, and other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, all which are hereunto annexed.</p>
            <p>And whereas <hi>Van Trump</hi> in the accompt he gives of this Action, makes the occaſion of his coming back upon the Engliſh Fleet, the guarding of ſome Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant men richly laden from the <hi>Streights,</hi> which had been in fight with ſome of our Friggots: That action is ſet down in a Letter written by Captain <hi>Yong</hi> (here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto alſo annexed) whereby the occaſion, beginning and ending thereof is declared: And beſides, theſe very Ships which he pretends to come to protect or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcue, upon Saturday before had paſt by General <hi>Blake,</hi> and were gone to the Eaſtward.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>General <hi>Blakes</hi> Letter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have diſpatched away this Expreſs to your Honors, to give you an account of what paſt yeſterday be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and the Dutch Fleet being in <hi>Rye-Bay;</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Intelligence from Major <hi>Bourn,</hi> that <hi>Van Trump</hi> with Forty Sail was off the South-ſand head, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I made all poſſible ſpeed to ply up towards them, and yeſterday in the morning we ſaw them at Anchor in and near <hi>Dover</hi>-Road; being come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166192:5"/>Three Leagues of them, they weighed and ſtood away by a wind to the Eaſtward: We ſuppoſing their intention was to leave us to avoid the Diſpute of the Flag; about two hours after they altered their courſe, and bore directly with us, <hi>Van Trump</hi> the headmoſt, whereupon we lay by and put our ſelves into a fighting poſture, judging they had a reſolution to ingage; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come within Muſquet ſhot, I gave order to fire at his Flag, which was done thrice, after the third ſhot he let flie a Broad-ſide at us; Major <hi>Bourn,</hi> with thoſe Ships that came from the <hi>Downs,</hi> being eight, was then making towards us, we continued fighting till night, then our Ship being unable to ſail, by reaſon that all our Rigging and Sails were extreamly ſhattered, our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen-Maſt ſhot off, we came with advice off the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptains to an Anchor about three or four Leagues of the <hi>Neſs</hi> to refit our Ship, at which we labored all the night; this morning we eſpyed the Dutch Fleet about four Leagues diſtance from ours towards the Coaſt of <hi>France,</hi> and by advice of a Councel of War, it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ply to windward to keep the weather gage, and we are now ready to let fall our Anchor this Tide; what courſe the Dutch Fleet ſteers we do not well know, nor can we tell what harm we have done them, but we ſuppoſe one of them to be ſunk, and another of Thirty Guns we have taken, with the Captains of both, his Main-Maſt of the firſt being ſhot by the Board, and much water in the Hold, made Captain <hi>Lawſons</hi> men to forſake her. We have ſix men of ours ſlain, and nine or ten deſperatly wounded, and twenty five more not without danger, amongſt them our Maſter and one of his Mates, and other Officers: We have received about ſeventy great Shot in our Hull and Maſts, in our Salls
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:166192:5"/>and Rigging without number, being engaged with the whole Body of the Fleet for the ſpace of four hours: And the Mark at which they aimed, we muſt needs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a great Mercy that we had no more harm, and our hope the Righteous God will continue the ſame unto us, if there do ariſe a War between us; they being firſt in the Breach, and ſeeking an Occaſion to Quarrel, and watching as it ſeems, an Advantage to brave us upon our own Coaſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant, <hi>Robert Blake.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From aboard the</hi> James, <hi>three Leagues off the</hi> Hydes, <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                     <hi>of</hi> May, 1652.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>The Information of Captain <hi>William Brandley,</hi> taken before his Excellency the Lord General <hi>Cromwel,</hi> and <hi>Denis Bond</hi> Eſquire, at <hi>Dover</hi> the <hi>22<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> of May, <hi>1652.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHo ſaith, That Wedneſday morning lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving General <hi>Blake</hi> off from the <hi>Neſſe</hi> with eleven Ships, <hi>(viz.)</hi> The <hi>James, Victory, Garland,</hi> the <hi>Speaker, Ruby, Saphine, Conturion, Star, Portſmouth, Martin, Mormaid</hi> and a Merchants Ship in the States ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and between ſeven and eight a clock in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing came to <hi>Dover</hi> Road, and fell in among part of <hi>Van Trump</hi>'s Fleet, and hayling ſeveral of their Ships, and asking who wore the Flag, he was anſwered by three or four of them, That he was <hi>Van Trump,</hi> and that they ſhould well wit, as his own men who were aboard with him that underſtood Dutch did interpret to him; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon this Informant went home to his own General, being ſome three Leagues to Weſtward of him, to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:166192:6"/>whom he gave the ſaid Accompt; which ſo ſoon as he had done, his General made all the haſte he could to <hi>Dover</hi> Road with thoſe Ships that were with him, and being come about three Leagues onward of his way, he this Informant and the reſt of the Fleet diſcerned <hi>Van Trump</hi> and his Fleet weighing their Anchors, and perceived them to make towards the <hi>French</hi> Coaſt about four Leagues from the place where they Anchor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and General <hi>Blake</hi> ſteering his courſe towards the <hi>Downs</hi> to the reſt of his Fleet, for which this Informant had ſeen the Orders of the Councel of State to him ſo to do; and being come up as high as <hi>Holſtone,</hi> they perceived a Ship came from the Eaſtwards towards the Dutch Fleet, not being able to fetch <hi>Van Trump,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Leeward of him, ſhot off a piece; and <hi>Van Trump</hi> bore up to the ſaid Ship, and within a quarter of an hour after, <hi>Van Trump</hi> ſhot off a Piece, and put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad his Pendant, and bore up on General <hi>Blake</hi> and the Fleet that was with him, and a little to the Eaſt of <hi>Sandgate</hi> Caſtle, he came up with all his Fleet, being Two and fourty Sail, to General <hi>Blake,</hi> and himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the head-moſt ſhip, having his Flag on his Main Top, came within ſhot of General <hi>Blake;</hi> whereupon General <hi>Blake</hi> ſhot at his Flag, and he not taking the ſame down, he ſhot a ſecond, and a third; upon which <hi>Van Trump</hi> taking in his Pendant, put out his Red Flag under his <hi>Holland</hi> Colours, and preſently after gave a Broad-ſide to General <hi>Blake,</hi> and thereupon General <hi>Blake</hi> anſwered him with another, and both the Fleets were engaged.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Brandley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:166192:6"/>
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Baſtean Tunemant</hi> late Captain of the Ship called the St. <hi>Lawrence,</hi> taken before his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency the Lord General <hi>Cromwel</hi> and <hi>Dennis Bond</hi> Eſquire, at <hi>Dover, 22 May, 1652.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHo ſaith, He came from <hi>Fluſhing</hi> about fourteen days ſince under the Command of Admiral <hi>Van Trump</hi> with two and forty ſail of Ships, and that they lay with their Fleet about four days between <hi>Zealand</hi> and <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> and from thence they came to <hi>Dover</hi> Road on Tueſday laſt about ten a clock in the morning, and there Anchored until Wedneſday about twelve a clock and then weighed Anchor, they made off towards the <hi>French</hi> Coaſt about two <hi>Dutch</hi> Leagues, where a ſhip of the States of <hi>Holland</hi> came up towards them, and made a waft with his Flag to <hi>Van Trump</hi> who bore up to that ſhip, and he ſaw a boat go from that ſhip aboard <hi>Van Trump,</hi> who thereupon preſently made all the ſail he could, and came through all his Fleet, and made with all the haſte he could towards General <hi>Blake</hi> and his Fleet: and being come near him, he ſhot a Gun without a Ball, and then two Guns more with Balls, as he was informed; whereupon <hi>Van Trump</hi> ſhot one ſhot at General <hi>Blake,</hi> and then preſently fired a Broad-ſide at him, who fired his Guns luſtily again at him, and the Fight began about four a clock in the afternoon, and continued till night. And he ſaith, That his ſhip one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was taken; and being demanded what was their Signal to fight, he ſaith, That when their Admiral hung out his Red Flag under the States Colours, they were to fall on: And ſaith, That when he ſaw their Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals Red Flag hung out, he perceived they were in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and then he did the beſt he could.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſtean Tunemant.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:166192:7"/>
            <head>The further Examination of <hi>Baſtean Tunemant</hi> Captain of the St. <hi>Lawrence,</hi> taken the ſame day before the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons aforeſaid.</head>
            <p>VVHo being demanded, whether he with four other <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships were not met by the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew</hi> and two other <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships near <hi>Calice</hi> about five weeks ſince, and whether they did ſtrike Top-ſails to them; He ſaith they did meet thoſe <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships and did ſtrike their Top-ſails to them; and after their arrival in <hi>Holland,</hi> their Admiral <hi>Van Trump</hi> asked this Examinant why he did ſtrike ſail to them, ſaying, Were you not as ſtrong as they? and being ſo, why were you afraid? And further ſaith, That the Owners of their Ships did likewiſe uſe words to them to the ſame effect.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Cornelius Teby</hi> late Lieutenant to the Ship St. <hi>Lawrence,</hi> taken the ſame day before the perſons aforeſaid.</head>
            <p>WHo ſaith, About fourteen days ſince he came from <hi>Fluſhing</hi> and joyned with Admiral <hi>Van Trump</hi> to the Eaſt of <hi>Oſtend</hi> about ten days ſince, and lay three days between <hi>Dunkirk</hi> and the <hi>North-furlong</hi> and came from thence to <hi>Dover</hi> Road on Tueſday be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ten and eleven a clock, having two and forty ſail of Ships, and there they anchored until Wedneſday about one a clock, and then weighed Anchor and made towards the Coaſt of <hi>France</hi> about four or five Leagues; where he ſaith, There came a Ship from the Weſt-ward and ſpake with their Admiral, who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon preſently bore up to General <hi>Blake,</hi> and when he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:166192:7"/>came near, General <hi>Blake</hi> made a ſhot without a Ball at their Admirals Flag, and after that two more ſhots, and their Admiral did not take down his Flag, but made one ſhot at General <hi>Blake,</hi> and preſently after fired a Broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and then General <hi>Blake</hi> fired at him; and as ſoon as their Admiral had fired his Broad-ſide, he hung out his Red Flag under the States Colours, and upon that their whole Fleet engaged according to Signal and Orders. The Fight began about four a clock, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued about four hours. He ſaith, The ſaid Ship <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> was a Merchants ſhip hired by the States of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for four moneths, at 1300. Gilders <hi>per</hi> moneth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Cornelius Teby.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Shipco Focus</hi> Captain of the St. <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> now priſoner, taken the ſame day, before the perſons aforeſaid.</head>
            <p>WHo ſaith, That about fourteen days ſince he came from <hi>Texel,</hi> and joyned with Admiral <hi>Van Trumps</hi> Fleet before <hi>Skevelyn,</hi> and laying three or four between <hi>Zealand</hi> and <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> they came on Tueſday laſt about noon to <hi>Dover</hi> Road, where they Anchored until Wedneſday Twelve a clock, and then weighed Anchor; they made off towards the coaſt of <hi>France</hi> about Two or Three Dutch Leagues, where a ſhip from the Weſtward made towards their Admiral, who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately heaved out all his Sails, and made towards the Engliſh Fleet that came from the Weſtward with General <hi>Blake;</hi> how the Fight began he knoweth not, being a great diſtance off; but ſeeing his Admiral fight he fought likewiſe, according to his Orders.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Shipco Focus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:166192:8"/>
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Peter Johnſon</hi> Lieutenant to <hi>Shipco Focus</hi> Captain of the St. <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> taken the ſame day before the perſons aforeſaid.</head>
            <p>WHo ſaith, About Fourteen days ſince he came from <hi>Texels,</hi> and joyned with Admiral <hi>Van Trump</hi> at <hi>Skevelyn</hi> about Three days after, and after they lay about Three days between <hi>Dunkirk</hi> and the North-furlong; and from thence they came to <hi>Dover</hi> Road on Tueſday about Ten a clock in the morning, and anchored there till Wedneſday about Twelve a clock, and then weighed Anchor and made towards the French coaſt about Five Leagues, where a Dutch ſhip of War came up to them, and ſpake with Admiral <hi>Van Trump,</hi> who thereupon bare up with all the ſail he could to the Engliſh General and his Fleet; but who began firſt to ſhoot he knoweth not: And being asked why he fought, he ſaith, That when the Admiral hung forth his Red Flag, they were to do the beſt they could; and ſeeing their other ſhips fight, they fought likewiſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>The further Examination of <hi>Cornelius Teby,</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant to the abovenamed Captain <hi>Tunemant,</hi> taken the ſame day before the perſons aforeſaid.</head>
            <p>WHo ſaith, That his Captain told him, that Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral <hi>Van Trump</hi> blam'd him for ſtriking ſail to the Engliſh Ships, ſaying, That he had marryed a yong Wife, and therefore was afraid, and made haſte home.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Cornelius Teby.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <p>WE whoſe Names are hereunder written, do hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly take leave to certifie the ſtate of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:166192:8"/>betwixt Us and the Dutch Fleet, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Upon the Nineteenth of this preſent <hi>May</hi> we had Intelligence, That they were off the South-foreland, conſiſting in the whole of about Forty two ſail, we plyed up with our Ships as faſt as poſſible, and being off <hi>Foulſton,</hi> eſpyed the Dutch Fleet to ride at Anchor near <hi>Dover,</hi> as ſoon as the Tide preſented we plyed towards them; whereupon they weighed and ſtood to the Southward, Three Leagues to the windward of our ſhips: we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by imagining they had not any intent to ingage with us, laid our ſhips about, and within half an hour <hi>Van Trump</hi> with all his Fleet bore up upon us; and being near, our General gave Order to fire at the Dutch Flag to ſtrike; which they refuſing, we ſhot again; they ſtill refuſed to ſtrike, but ſhot a Piece at our Flag, and ſhot it through, we then being within Muſquet ſhot one of the other: Then the third time we fired a Gun at his Flag, which was no ſoone done, but he fired his whole broad ſide at us, and ſo we engaged, and went on fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from half an hour paſt Four that afternoon till Nine of the clock at night, and then we anchored to fit our ſhip in a poſture for the next morning; the Dutch Fleet being to the ſouthward of us Three Leagues, next morning directed their courſe for <hi>France;</hi> whereupon ſeeing of them do ſo, we plyed up to the Downs: This we humbly certifie, and the truth thereof will upon all occaſions teſtifie, and have hereunto ſubſcribed our hands the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of this preſent <hi>May,</hi> 1652.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Robert Moulton</hi> jun.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Gilſon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Redwood.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Anth: Jackſon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Henry Coradall.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>Major <hi>Bourn</hi>'s Relation.</head>
            <p>UPon the Eighteenth of <hi>May,</hi> the Wind being at North-Eaſt, the weather ſomething haiſie, about
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:166192:9"/>Ten in the morning we ſaw a great Fleet on the back ſide of the <hi>Goodwyn ſand,</hi> which lay with their ſayls hayl'd up, and drove to the fouthward the later Tyde of Ebb in land; about twelve they were ſo nigh, that we plainly deſcried them to be all Men of War, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of One and forty in number, one whereof had a Flag at the main Top-maſt head, the reſt Jacks and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, <hi>Hollands</hi> Colours, at which time they were near the <hi>South ſands</hi> Head: There was in the <hi>Downs</hi> the <hi>Andrew, Triumph, Fairfax, Entrance, Centurion, Adventure, Aſſurance, Greyhound,</hi> and the <hi>Seven Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> all the reſt of the Fleet being with the General to the Weſtward, by whoſe ſpecial Command I wore a Flag at the main Top-maſt head; the appearance of which I humbly conceive was one cauſe amongſt others which moved their General to ſend two Frigots to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, which as ſoon as I perceived plying into the Road, I ſent out the <hi>Greyhound</hi> to examine them, and know the ground of their Approach; who returned this Anſwer to the Captain, That they had a Meſſage from their Admiral to the Commander in the <hi>Downs,</hi> at which he made ſayl towards me, permitted them to come in, the two Frigots came near and ſaluted the Flag, and then the Captains came on Board, whoſe names were, one <hi>Tyſon,</hi> and the other <hi>Aldred,</hi> who brought this Meſſage from their Admiral <hi>Van Trump,</hi> That by reaſon of much Northerly Winds, he with his Fleet was put the ſouthward farther then he intended, and having Anchored the day before off <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his ſhips had loſt Anchors and Cables, and ſo were forced to leewards; but withal declared, that they had ſpecial Command from their Admiral to ſignifie thus much, That it was the onely cauſe of their coming
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:166192:9"/>to prevent any thoughts or miſaprehenſions, for that he had not the leaſt purpoſe to offer injury to any of the Engliſh Nation, but for fear leaſt any noiſe or Alarum ſhould be given either at Land or Sea, he thought good to ſend this meſſage. And further, the one of them in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſaid, that their Admiral <hi>Trump</hi> would have come himſelf into the Road, but that he was not willing to breed any difference about his Flag, foraſmuch as he had not order to take it down: To whom I replied, That I preſumed there would be no new thing required of them, and neither more nor leſſe would be expected from them, but what they knew to be the ancient Right of this Nation; and withal I deſired them to return this Anſwer from me to their General, That their Meſſage was civil, that our General was to the Weſt-ward, whom I looked for hourly, and that received; and if what they delivered was ſo intended, I deſired the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality there of might be manifeſted by their ſpeedy draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off from this place with their Fleet, for elſe this their appearance would be otherwiſe expounded; and ſo I diſmiſſed them, who made ſail to their Admiral who lay off the South-Sands head. I expected them to come into the Road every moment, and therefore was in readineſs with the ſmall ſtrength I had under my charge; ſo ſoon as the two Friggots before mentioned came back to their General, they all made Sail and ſtood toward <hi>Dover,</hi> and there they came to an Anchor that Tyde. At the firſt appearance of them, after I had made them certainly to be the <hi>Holland</hi> Fleet, I did according to my duty give ſuch an Accompt thereof to the Right Honorable the Councel of State, as the time and other buſineſs would admit, &amp; withal I immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:166192:10"/>diſpatched a Ketch to our General, who met with the adviſe thereof that night about <hi>Neſſe.</hi> All the next night we lay in readineſs, our Anchors apeck, and kept two Friggots one at a diſtance from the other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us and them, giving them Inſtructions to make a Signal to me either night or day, that I might under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their motion whether towards, the General or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, to the end I might the better be able to order my ſelf and the party with me to the beſt advantage for ſecurity of the Generals Fleet and our ſelves. In the morning about ten a clock I received advice from the General being a little to the Weſt-ward of <hi>Foulſtone,</hi> and according to Order received from him, calculated the time and Tyde, ſo that we might moſt opportunely make conjunction of our Forces. About twelve a clock I ſet ſail out of the <hi>Downs,</hi> the wind being Eaſterly, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after I perceived the <hi>Hollanders</hi> to be under ſail ſome of them, and the reſt making ready: we ſteer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alongſt, and when we came as high as the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreland, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> Fleet was got off the Shore and were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Channel over plying to wind-ward towards <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,</hi> at which time I ſaw our General and thoſe with him, and within an hour after or thereabouts, the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Fleet bore up and made Sail toward him; we haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned towards him, and hope I may ſay, ſeaſonably came in, for by that time the Guns were fired betwixt the Admirals, we were with the body of their Fleet and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged with them from half an hour paſt four in the afternoon till it was dark; what execution we did upon them they beſt know, I ſhall not determine it, but ſurely they were ſenſible of us, for they did their utmoſt to decline us and avoid our coming near, which we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavored
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:166192:10"/>by all means; but their Admiral leading the Van, they all made ſail after him, and ſo ſhot them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Leeward of us, and ſo left the Rear of the Fleet to us, which we endeavored to ſever from the reſt, and accordingly did in part break the Body, and ſome of us who were the neareſt and had the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Wind, fell upon the Stern moſt, who I ſuppoſe found it hot work; the one of them of thirty Guns we took which fought ſtoutly, another of the ſame force ſo lamed, her main Maſt ſhot down, and having much water in Hold yielded, and the Captain thereof came in to our Boat to ſave himſelf; the night coming on and no hope left him, I preſume ſhe ſunk in the night. We not knowing what might be the iſſue of this beginning, endeavored to finde out our Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, to the end we might receive Inſtructions how to order our ſelves in the morning, expecting certainly to proſecute the buſineſs then, for which end we preſently came to an Anchor, becauſe we would be near them in the morning, but they did not ſtop, ſo that in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we could ſcarce diſcern them at Top-maſt head; by which we concluded that they were bound over to the coaſt of <hi>France,</hi> and were not willing to try it farther at this time, and therefore that evening plyed it up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Foulſtone,</hi> and between that and <hi>Dover</hi> anchored again, and the next day came into the <hi>Downs.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>29 May. 1652.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your very aſſured Friend and Servant in the Work of God, <hi>N. BOURN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:166192:11"/>
            <head>Inſtructions given to the Dutch captains by <hi>Van Trump. Martin Harperts Trump</hi> Knight, and Lieutenant Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Frizeland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THat the Vice-Admiral Scout (or he that keeps the Watch) at night, and all the Captains be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing under his Colour already preſent, or thoſe that yet are to come under his Command, upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion that may befal, may know how to govern him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf duly, he is to obſerve the ſeventh and eighth Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of his Lieutenant Admiral's Inſtruction, whoſe Content doth follow word for word.</p>
            <div type="article">
               <head>The ſeventh Article.</head>
               <p>The Commanders or Captains of the Squadrons already fitted, or yet to be prepared, are commanded to Maintain and Defend the Ships of theſe Countreys from all Viſitations or Searchings, without compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending all neceſſary Queſtions in the Sea, or demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſhewing of their Paſſes and Bills of Lading; which according to the eighth Article of the Sea-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty made the ſeventeenth of <hi>December,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred and fifty, with the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inſerted in following words, may be required of whomſoever it may be, defending them againſt all and every one that would offend them, delivering them from the hands of any that may have taken them; and in ſuch Caſes to uſe all their power to overcome ſuch ſtrong Ships, doing all that may be requiſite by their Commiſſions and ordinary Inſtructions, according to the Cuſtom of Sea-faring men, to the ſervice of the Countrey.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And to hinder that the ſaid forbidden Goods of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terband,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:166192:11"/>whether they be marked or ſigned, and are regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by the Article immediately preceding, not to be carried to the Enemies of the ſaid King of</hi> Spain, <hi>and under Pretence thereof to hinder the Freedom and Safety of Shipping and Commerce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is agreed, That the Ships of the Subjects and Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the</hi> United Provinces <hi>come into any Harbor of the ſaid King, and intending to go thence to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys of his Enemies, ſhall onely be bound to deliver and to ſhew to the Officers of the Spaniſh Ports or other States of the ſaid Lord King, from whence they intend to part to ſhew their Paſſes, containing and ſpecifying their Lading of their Ships, atteſted and marked with the ordinary Seal and Marks, and acknowledged by the Officers of the Admiralty in the Parts whence they firſt are parted, ſhewing the place which they intend to ſail unto, altogether in an ordinary and accuſtomed Form; After which having their Paſſes in the ſaid form, they are no more to be moleſted, nor ſearched or detained and ſtayed, under what pretext ſoever it might be.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>The eighth Article.</head>
               <p>If they come to fight with other ſtrange Ships, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of freeing themſelves or hindering the viſiting and ſearching of the ſhips of theſe Countreys, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming the ſame, they are to bring in or to ſend ſuch conquered ſhips, with ſufficient Information of what is paſt, that it may be right repreſented in the Admiralty of the Quarter out of which the Conqueror did part. Datum in the Ship <hi>Brederode,</hi> this 25 <hi>May,</hi> 1652.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Signed, <hi>M: Harperts Trump.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:166192:12"/>
            <head>APPENDIX.</head>
            <p>IT is further here commanded, That all Commanders and Captains under the ſaid Colour or Flags, ſhall at all hours keep ready their Canons and Fore-Arms, and coming towards any Foreign Ship of War, making all things ready, and making haſte as much as weather and wind will give them leave, to go to the reſt of our Ships, and there remain in a good poſture: That obſerving well the ſign of War, Defenſive and Offenſive (by reaſon of freeing from ſearching or viſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Ships of theſe Countries, or otherwiſe) they may paſs according to the ſign, which ſign of War ſhall be a Red Flag, under the Prince, hanging and ſtreaming on the Admirals Great. Which ſeeing every one, he ſhal endeavor to his utmoſt to do what poſſible he can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the parties advantage, taking them, and to bring the gotten Ships under the Flag, thereupon to reſolve and to diſpoſe as is fit; but aſſoon as the ſaid Red Flag on the ſaid Admirals great Rodol is taken in or off, all Actions of Hoſtility ſhall ceaſe.</p>
            <p>It is alſo expreſly forbidden to make any unneceſſary ſhots of Honor, but rather to keep and well to manage the Powder and Shot of the Countrey; but yet coming to any Foreign Ship of War, whereby it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to give ſome ſalutation by ſhooting for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the Countrey; In that caſe they are to obſerve and maintain in all honeſty the Honor of our Countrey, according as the Commanders or Captains of the Foreign Ships of War ſhall do the like to the Lieutenant Admiral, or to thoſe that are in his Place
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:166192:12"/>and Command; and alſo be wary to do no harm by the ſaid ſhooting for Honor.</p>
            <p>Further, whenſoever ſome croſs the Seas, and any of the Fleet (whether he be under the Colour or a part croſſing) diſcovering any Foreign Ship, following the third Article of his Letter of Commiſſion, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of any preparation or gathering of Ships of War, whereſoever it may be, or that already ſome Ships or Fleet ſhall have paſſed; Then he is to learn, and obſerve very ſtrictly the number of the ſaid ſhips, their Arming, Guns and Men, of the ſaid preparation; and likewiſe what courſe ſuch a Fleet that may be paſſed may have taken, and thereof adviſe, and ſend in all haſte word to the Admiral or Commander for the ſervice of the Countreys, that thereupon order may be taken ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly: And the general token or ſign ſhall be to diſcover the Sea, coming together or to a Rendezvouz to advertiſe together of ſuch Fleets as may be paſſed, whether they may be gone to any Haven of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys or not, or concerning any matter important to the ſervice of theſe Countreys; and therefore at every half hour marked by his Hour-glaſs, to ſhoot off a great Piece of Ordnance, whereupon every one hearing the unuſual ſign of that ſhot, is to anſwer in like maner, and in all haſte go towards the place where the foreſaid ſhot hath been made, that ſpeedily he may meet with the other ſhips, and there to do what the Admiral or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander with the Councel of War, for the good and ſervice of theſe Countreys ſhall finde fit to be done. <hi>Datum ut Supra.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Signed,</hi> M: Harperts Trump.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:166192:13"/>
            <head>Captain <hi>Yongs</hi> Letter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS I was coming to the Weſtward to take the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Weſt-guard the twelfth inſtant off the <hi>Start,</hi> I deſcried a Fleet of ſhips about a dozen ſail, coming from the Southward, being Admiral, Vice and Rere in the Fleet, ſo that I did conceive them to be <hi>Sir George Ayſcu's</hi> Fleet; but I making ſail off to them, found them a Fleet of Hollanders came from <hi>Janua</hi> and <hi>Legorn;</hi> Thoſe three with Flags were States-men of War their Convoyers, the other Merchants ſhips, ſome upwards of Thirty Guns and ſome under; ſo I bore with the Admiral, and did ſend him by my Maſter, That he ſhould ſtrike his Flag, and did deſire a right underſtanding might be between us before any Blood was ſhed in the controverſie; on this the Admiral took in his Flag and put abroad a Pendent, he ſaid he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> but his name I know not, but the ſhip hath two wilde men or the like in her ſtern, and ſome other things between them, ſhe hath ſome Thirty eight guns: ſo then the Vice-Admiral came up with me with his Flag abroad, being a ſhip of Forty two Guns, ſo I called to perſwade him to ſtrike, he bid me come on board and ſtrike it, ſo I ſent my Boat on board to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him to it to prevent the loſs of Blood, if it might be, but he ſent me word by my Maſter he would not ſtrike; ſo then being fitted for it, I came up very near on the Weather-quarter, yet before I fired, I called to the Captain my ſelf to take in his Flag, but he ſaid he would not; ſo then I commanded a Broad-ſide and a Volley of ſmall ſhot to be fired on him, and I received the like from him again: Thus we paſt ſome four or
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:166192:13"/>five Broad-ſides each at other, though I was forced to be at ſome further diſtance from him then the firſt, I fearing the Admiral would have laid me on Board on the Weather-ſide, he having fitted his ſhip, and come up Main-ſail, and all to gain the Wind of me, forced me to keep the Wind of him; then Captain <hi>Reynolds</hi> being come up fair within ſhot of his weather quarter, having fired ſome ſix Guns be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at the Rear Admiral, as he came in amongſt us; ſo he fired part of a broad ſide at the Vice-Admiral, juſt at that inſtant as he was taking in his Flag, the <hi>Recovery</hi> being come up even within ſhot juſt as his Flag was in, and the Rear-Admiral ſtruck likewiſe: So I ſent aboard the Admiral, That I did demand the Vice-Admiral, either in his perſon or his ſhip to carry into Port, to make good what damage was done: He told my Maſter, he did not meddle in the leaſt himſelf as yet, as long as it was onely about ſtriking the Flag, the which he ſaid was now taken in; but if I ſought any further matter, as the ſurprizal of him or the ſhip, he was bound and would aſſiſt him, ſhe being the States ſhip as well as he, not then knowing, or could take any notice of any further intentions: So I deſired Captain <hi>Reynolds</hi> and Captain <hi>Chapman</hi> to come on board to conſult with me what further to do in it, it being near night; and it was the judgment of us all, not to proceed any further in it, the Flags being taken in, by reaſon the Treaty being between the Nations at preſent, the caſe of Breach of the Peace might not be any way imputed on our part. I have received ſome damage in my Hull ſail and rigging, the which I ſhall ſoon, God willing, get repaired again; I had one
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:166192:14"/>man even as good as killed out-right, dyed ſince, and ſome Four wounded, but I hope they will recover: For my own part, I bleſs the Lord for it, I am very well; I do believe I gave him his belly full of it, for he ſent me word he had Order from the States, That if he ſtruck he ſhould loſe his head; but at length he did ſtrike, which makes me conceive he had enough of it.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Preſident, Plymouth Sound,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 14. 1652.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Honors humble Servant at command, <hi>Anth: Young.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="report">
            <head>A Paper delivered by the Lords Ambaſſadors to the Councel of State, the Third of <hi>June, 1652. new ſtile.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Honorable Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE are here by reaſon of and unhappy an unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Miſchance; An horrible Report hath amazed us, That a Fight at Sea ſhould have been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Fleet of this Commonwealth and of the United Provinces, and That ours ſhould have been the reaſon of this unfortunate buſineſs, That we began the Fight, and that thereupon is fought moſt cruelly; and that from thence the Rumor of the breaking of the Treaty, and of open War (which ſhould be very near at hand between the two Nations) was ſpread: We aſtoniſhed by this ſad Report, direct our ſelves to this Honorable Aſſembly, and do Declare before God, and out of all our Hearts, That the Fact, ſo as it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, is committed without the knowledge, and againſt the will of the States of the United Provinces
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:166192:14"/>our Lords, and of us their Ambaſſadors. Moreover we do affirm, That the Hearts of ours do deſire nothing but Unity, Peace, League, and a very near Friendſhip with this Commonwealth, and hope that with all their wiſhes. In the mean while, we do think it not to be amiſs, if we give notice unto your Honors, That we have received Letters from the Admiral of the Fleet of the United Provinces, Dated the Thirtieth of the laſt Moneth, wherein the occaſion and reaſon of the ſaid Fight-quite otherwiſe is declared then the common Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port is: For the truth of which buſineſs, we ſuppoſe to be convenient to inquire exactly; But this is worth obſervation in the mean time, That our Admiral <hi>Trump</hi> in the ſame Letter doth declare plainly to have no other Order from the Lords the States, then to ſail about, and to view the ſhore and coaſts of our country, as far as <hi>Oſtend</hi> and <hi>Newport</hi> and no farther. By which it doth appear as clearly as the Sun is under Heaven, That by all means the States of the United Provinces have had no minde to attempt any thing againſt the Fleet or other ſhips of this Commonwealth. If any thing then in this buſineſs be done otherwiſe then it ought to be, this doth not concern the ſaid States, but them which have executed the ſaid buſines, and let them make it good. We have been here now almoſt ſix Moneths about the concluding of a League, by ſpecial Order of the ſaid States, and have delivered ſome days ago to your Commiſſioners a Paper, in which not onely the different Points touching the Treaty, but alſo the means by which the ſame could be brought to a good Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and reconciled one with another, were ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared; ſo that vve did expect nothing every day,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:166192:15"/>but a happy end to ſo good a Work; and truly that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent matter may in very few hours be finiſhed. But who ſhould ever believe that ſo Noble a Work, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired vvith ſo many vviſhes of all honeſt men, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of all the Churches of the Reformed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, ſhould be cut off or hindred by any ſuch imprudent and turbulent man (whoſoever he may be) without knowledge and againſt the will of the Lords the States? By Law of Nature and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms of all Nations is very well known, That he to whom a Charge is given in particular things, an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador in Publique Buſineſs going beyond the limit of their Commiſſions, a General of an Army Depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating without order of his Superiors any Grounds of the Neighbors; a wilde beaſt doing any mifchief after it hath broken its bond, that not the Maſters but thoſe that have done the wrong are obliged, eſpecially if the diſapproving of the ſame Maſters followeth thereupon; which without queſtion (if the buſineſs be ſo as it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated) is to be expected from the States of the United Provinces. In the mean while we make no doubt, that to attempt any Hoſtility before the other party is heard, cannot be approved neither by God, nor by any men, eſpecially Chriſtians. It is a Cuſtom by all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Nations to demand reſtitution of their Goods if any trouble be done, and in caſe Satisfaction be given or offered, to lay aſide all Hoſtility. And it is no wonder that all Nations are ſo much againſt War and inclined to eſtabliſh a Peace, the War being plainly a cruel mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, a world of evil, and a meer deluge of innocent blood; therefore the moſt holy Fathers of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on have expreſly declared the War (although juſt) to be
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:166192:15"/>execrable, eſpecially in relation to the Chriſtians, who are taught by their meekeſt Savior to ſpare other mens blood as well as their own. But amongſt all kinde of Wars, is this to be reputed the moſt deteſtable and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible if between theſe Nations War be riſen. Truly the experience teacheth us, that the beſt and ſtrongeſt Wine (if it be corrupted) becomes the ſowreſt Vineger; and indeed if two Nations having been friends of old times, of the ſame Religion, lovers of Liberty, joyning upon the ſame Sea, next Neighbors, both Valiant and Warlike be claſhed together, what is to be expected but the Ruine of both, and as the Proverb ſaith, a Cad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean Victory. And what elſe is this then to afflict and depreſſe your Friends and Companions in Religion to pleaſe our Enemies, and to give occaſion openly for to hurt them both. An Author, being none of the leaſt amongſt yours, hath very well compared, as we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, both the Nations to two earthen Pots driving in the Sea with this device, If we hurt, we break; He hit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it very well that honeſt man, and we may believe you are of the ſame opinion. But if the two Nations come to an Agreement, Oh Lord, what ſtore of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs will this bring forth! The true Gods Service will be eſtabliſhed, the Sea be quiet, and Opportunity taken away from all Enemies to trouble them both; all Companions in Religion be reſoiled, and which is to be reputed the chiefeſt of all, To the moſt good and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Lord, Praiſes and Thankſgiving will be lift up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Heavens. We conclude then, moſt Honorable Lords, and inſtantly demand and deſire, ſo as we have longed to propoſe to your Honors this three days ſince;</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:166192:16"/>
            <p>Firſt, That a Copy may be given unto us of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the things that are paſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That we may ſend that over by your leave to our Lords the States, and that the other part being heard, the truth of the Buſineſs may be known.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That in the mean while all things may be kept whole and untouched.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That by no means the Buſineſs of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding of the Treaty be put off, and that ſuch unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Miſchances may be avoided, and an everlaſting Peace may be eſtabliſhed between both the Nations.</p>
            <p>All which we deſire of all our hearts, the great and bountiful God the Author of Peace will be pleaſed to grant us.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed, Cats. G: Schaep. Vandeperre.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Tranſlation of the LETTER of the Admiral <hi>Trump</hi> to the States Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, mentioned in the precedent Paper.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>High and Mighty Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY laſt Letter was of the twentieth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, ſent by the Meſſenger that brought my Inſtruction aboard, ſince when I croſſed the Sea before the Maſe, <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingen, Oſtend</hi> and <hi>Newport,</hi> until the twenty four of the ſame Moneth, when we were forced to caſt our Anchor, and ſtay there in a hard weather and a rough ſea, until the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:166192:16"/>ſix in the morning: The weather grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fairer, and being under Sail, divers Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of the <hi>Direction</hi> came aboard, complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That they loſt their Anchors and Cables, ſome having but two Anchors &amp; two Cables left; It was reſolved, becauſe the wind did grow big, to go under the point of <hi>Dover</hi> for to prevent the loſs of our Ships. At one of the clock coming before Downs, we did ſend the Commander <hi>John Thiſſen</hi> from <hi>Fliſsingen,</hi> and Captain <hi>Peter Alders</hi> towards the Downs to the Commander <hi>Bourn,</hi> who was there with ſome Ships of the Parliament, whom they ſaluted in my Name, advertiſing him that we were bound to croſs the Sea about our coaſt; and that having loſt ſome Anchors by the laſt hard weather, we were forced to Anchor under <hi>Dover,</hi> to help one another, and ſo to return to our appointed limits; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving alſo no other order, but to protect our Merchants Ships and Fiſhermen, and to maintain the honor of our Country: That we therefore thought it fit to acquaint the ſaid Commander with the ſame, becauſe he ſhould not ſuſpect any thing to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; who alſo with much courteſie did ſalute
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:166192:17"/>me, and thank me for this notice. Upon the twenty nine, at two of the clock, we made ſail, the wind North eaſt, good weather, ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling towards <hi>Calice,</hi> with intention to croſs towards our coaſt, for to provide us of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Anchors: Coming about <hi>Calice</hi> Cliff, we met with Captain <hi>Ioris van Sanen</hi> of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi> coming out the <hi>Streights,</hi> with Captain <hi>Hugeluyt,</hi> having in their Company ſeven rich Merchants Ships, who are eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above fifty Tuns of Gold, who he left the twenty nine at Anchor, right againſt <hi>Feverley,</hi> where about twelve Ships of the Parliament did lye, and divers Frigots came to ſee them; and for as much as the ſaid <hi>Ioris van Sanen</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the twenty two of <hi>May,</hi> about <hi>Goutſtart,</hi> was met a Frigot of the Parliament, who fiercely ſet upon him for to make him ſtrike, and againſt whom he defended him neer about two hours, and ſo was left by the ſaid Frigot, whereupon the ſaid Commander <hi>Hugeluyt,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Van Sanen,</hi> ſhould endeavor for to finde out our main Fleet, and to give us no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it; as he did accordingly, fearing much, That the ſaid Merchants Veſſels alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy might be taken: Whereupon I preſently
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:166192:17"/>went thither, to take them under my protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and if they were taken, to put them at liberty, if it was poſsible, according to the ſeventh and eighth Articles of my Inſtruction of the ſixteenth inſtant. Upon the way we met fifteen Ships and Frigots of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, among whom one was an Admiral, whom I intended to view, taking in all my Sails, except both my Murſhot Sails, whom we did avail until the middeſt of the ſtangs. Being within a Canon-ſhot, he ſhot a Ball over our Ship, we anſwered not, he ſhot an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, to which we anſwered with one; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently he gives me a broad ſide, being within a Muſquet ſhot, and ſhot all his ſide through our Ship and Sails: Divers were wounded, ſome with the loſs of their Arms, ſome other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; thereupon we preſently gave him our broadſide, not knowing what they intended, which for as yet I know not, becauſe they did not ſpeak a word to us, neither we to them, and we fell thereupon to a general fight. In mean while came the Commander <hi>Bourn</hi> out the Downs, with twelve of ſuch like Ships and Frigots mounted, as he told him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the ſaid Commander <hi>John Thyſſen,</hi> and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:166192:18"/>Captain <hi>Peter Alders,</hi> being aboard of him with ſixty to ſeventy, and the Frigots with thirty eight to fifty pieces of Ordnance, who in the ſame while aſſaulted our Fleet from behinde; and we fought thus from half an hour paſt four till nine of the clock, the darkneſs departing us from another; when both the Admirals a little beyond the reach of their Ordnance caſt their Sails towards the Lee for to gather their Fleets, and to mend what was ſhot to pieces, we floated the whole night with a light on every Ship. The thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth in the morning, we ſaw the Engliſh Fleet driven windward from us, who made Sail and went towards <hi>Dover.</hi> We wanted two of our Ships, who were in the rear of our Fleet: The Captains, <hi>Tuynmans</hi> of <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourgh,</hi> and <hi>Siphe Fooks</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> both Ships of the Direction, whereof we found that of Captain <hi>Siphe Fooks</hi> about noon float<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without Maſt; The Skipper and the Officers declared unto us that they were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by three Ships of the Parliament two hours after Sunſet, who took from aboard the Captain and the Lieutenant, with four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen or fifteen men more, and putted inſtead
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:166192:18"/>of them many of the Engliſh; but they fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Ship would ſink, they took the flight, after they had plundred all in Hoſtile maner: They Declared alſo, That they ſee that the ſaid <hi>Tuynmans</hi> (being with them in the rear of our Fleet) an hour before was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: We intend with this Eaſterly wind to croſs to and fro, that we may finde out the ſaid <hi>Streight</hi> fearders, if it be poſsible, and with all other Ships with whom we may meet, to bring them ſafe in our Country: So ending was ſubſcribed</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M: Harp Trump.</signed>
               <dateline>Dated <date>the 30 of <hi>May,</hi> 1652.</date> from aboard the Ship.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="report">
            <head>The Lords Ambaſſadors ſecond Paper, 6 <hi>June.</hi> 1652.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>To the Councel of State of the Commonwealth of</hi> England.</head>
            <p>AS on Monday laſt the Ambaſſadors of the States of the <hi>United Provinces</hi> of the Netherlands, have ſaid before the moſt Illuſtrious Councel upon their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and faith, and have averred by the Witneſs of God, That the unlook'd for and untimely Sea-fight of the two Fleets happened without the knowledge and the will of the ſaid Lords States, and withal treating
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:166192:19"/>with the Councel about it with all uprightneſs, deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them a Copy of <hi>Trump</hi>'s Lettershimſelf, whereby it might the better appear to the Commonwealth, that the ſaid Lords States had commanded the ſaid <hi>Trump</hi> nothing elſe then to ſhip about the Coaſts and Havens of their Dominions, to ſhun all ſuſpitions and Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; even ſo now again the ſame Lords Ambaſſadors aſſure the moſt Illuſtrious Councel, That by the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Meſſenger they receive yeſterday, they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived all the Conſultations handled by the ſaid Lords States General from the 22<hi rend="sup">th</hi> until the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, day of the laſt Moneth (new ſtile) on which the ſaid Fight happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whereby it appears yet more clear, and the ſaid Lords Commiſſioners are more aſſured, that their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors gave at all no occaſion, no cauſe nor counſel, but rather they did breathe (as it were) and further with the ſame minde, care and zeal, a more ſtrict Friendſhip and mutual Alliance betwixt theſe two Nations, as it doth appear more clear then the ſun at noon, by their ſaid Lordſhips ſentence on the occaſion of an Anſwer to be ſent to the Proteſtant <hi>Swiſſers,</hi> made on the 23<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the the ſaid Moneth, a Copy whereof they now alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and offer to the ſaid moſt Illuſtrious Councel.</p>
            <p>Therefore the ſaid Lords Ambaſſadors intreat again this moſt ample Councel, That yielding due faith to ſo many Proteſtations, and to ſo many Teſtimonies, they would now upon their Demands with the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (as is underſtood) communicated two days ſince, they would at the ſooneſt give them ſuch an Anſwer as the ſaid Councel, according to their Wiſdom and Juſtice may ſeem good and neceſſary, to prevent great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er harm, and already imminent Dangers; And that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:166192:19"/>to theſe Evils a more ready Remedy may be applied, the ſame Lords Ambaſſadors would not have this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ignorant, that the Lord <hi>Newport,</hi> ſent by the Lords States to deliver to the Lords Ambaſſadors their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations, and ſignifie to them beſides their ſincere and plain Minde, ſince it now ſeems things did happen otherwiſe and againſt their Hope and Truſt, to think upon and prepare his Return, that ſo the better he might let them know in what ſtate and condition mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters now are, and what Remedy there may be applied; To which end the ſaid Lords Ambaſſadors do intreat this Councel to give freedom and leave to the ſaid Lord <hi>Newport,</hi> that he may chooſe ſome one of the Lords <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tates General ſhips, now either in the <hi>Thames</hi> or in other parts of this Commonwealth, abiding for his Tranſportation, or by any other means may return home. Given at <hi>Chelſey,</hi> 6 <hi>June,</hi> 1652. <hi>ſtilo novo.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed, <hi>J. Cats. G. Schaep. Vandeperre.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="report">
            <head>An Extract out of the Regiſter of the Reſolutions of the High and Mighty Lords, the States General of the United Provinces.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Thurſday the</hi> 28. <hi>of</hi> May, 1652.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>AFter that the Letter of the Evangelical Cantons in</hi> Switzerland <hi>and there aſſociated in Religion, dated the</hi> 14. <hi>of</hi> April <hi>laſt paſt, and yeſterday received, was this day again produced; It is upon deliberation reſolved and ordered to ſend them an Anſwer, and ſignifie, that their Lordſhips hath received the before mentioned Letter, and return great thanks for the Affection which they ſhew unto this State, and for their care for the Conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Reformed Religion, as alſo the Continua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:166192:20"/>of Peace and Concord amongſt this State and the Commonwealth of</hi> England; <hi>with a Declaration, That their Lordſhips will not fail to contribute all things that ſhall be neceſſary to promote the one and the other: And ſpecially a good Correſpondence with the ſaid Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, hoping the ſame of the ſaid Commonwealth. That it is true, that ſome extraordinary preparation of Ships of War was made, but to no other intention as to the ſafety of the Sea, and ſecurity of the Navigation and Trade of theſe Countreys. That to conclude, Their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips did wiſh to the ſaid Evangelical Cantons and their Religion-friends, all kinde of Proſperity, Peace, Safety and mutual Union, for the Exaltation of Gods moſt holy Name, Conſervation of the true Chriſtian Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and Proſperity of both ſides, States and Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="report">
            <head>The third Paper of the Lords Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, exhibited 13 <hi>Iune,</hi> 1652.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>To the Councel of State of the Commonwealth of</hi> England;</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Illuſtrious Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>EVen as both by vvord of mouth, and alſo by Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, we have ſignified to this Councel on the third and ſixth days of this moneth, taking God the ſearcher of Mans hearts to witneſs, that the moſt unhappy Fight of the ſhips of both Commonwealths did happen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the knowledge and will of the Lords States Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the United Netherlands; ſo alſo are we daily more and more aſſured both by Meſſages and Letters, witneſſing the moſt ſincere hearts of our ſaid Lords, and that with grief and aſtoniſhment they received the fatal
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:166192:20"/>News of that unhappy raſh Action; and that upon what we thereupon preſently ſent them word of, they did conſult and endeavor to finde out what Remedy chiefly may be applied to mitigate that raw and bloody Wound: To which end, they have written out for to gather a ſolemn Meeting or Parliament of all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, whereby we do not doubt but there will be provided for theſe Troubles (by Gods favor) ſuch a cure and preſent help, whereby not onely the outward cauſe of all further Evil may be taken away, but alſo by an Intern comfort the mindes may be redreſſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced again to a better hope of our Treaty in hand; Which thing being now moſt earneſtly agitated by our Lords for the common good of both Nations, to ſhun that deteſtable ſhedding of Chriſtian blood (ſo much deſired, and would be dearly bought by their common Enemies of both Nations, and of the Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) we again do crave this moſt Honorable Councel, and beſeech you, by the Pledges both of the common Religion and Liberty: mean while to ſuffer nothing to be done out of too much heat, that afterwards may prove neither revocable nor repairable by too late idle Vows and Wiſhes; but rather, that you would let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a kinde Anſwer without further delay upon our laſt Requeſt.</p>
            <p>Which we do again and again deſire ſo much the more, becauſe we underſtand, that the Ships of our Lords and of our Shippers both on the broad Sea, as in the Ports of this Commonwealth, ſome by force, ſome by fighting, are taken by your men and kept. Given at <hi>Chelſey</hi> 3/13 <hi>June,</hi> 1652.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed, <hi>J. Cats. G. Schaep. Vanderperre.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
